<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="website.xsl" ?>
 <page name="home" title="Home">
  <p>
   The Breakout group "Reclaim the Hardware Design Space!" on the <a
   href="http://lisp-ecoop.bknr.net">3rd European Lisp Workshop</a> is
   about creating hardware that is suited to dynamic programming
   languages in general, and LISP in particular.  We will be
   investigating current hardware technologies to find out what they
   have to offer for systems that are dynamic from the ground up.
  </p>
  <p>
   The breakout group is meant to provide a meeting point for
   researchers and practitioners working on hardware implementation
   techniques for dynamic languages.  To participate, you should know
   something about the implementation of dynamic languages, about
   hardware, or both.  You are not required to actually have created a
   LISP machine yourself, but you should be aware of some of the
   associated issues in order to take part in the discussion.
  </p>
  <p>
   Some of the topics of interest are:
   <ul>
    <li>Implementation of LISP-friendly CPUs in hardware</li>
    <li>Hardware assisted garbage collection</li>
    <li>Self-Synthesis and Hardware/Software Co-Design</li>
    <li>LISP based ASLs for hardware description and synthesis</li>
    <li>Techniques for CPU implementation on FPGAs</li>
    <li>Reengineering ancient CPUs in software or hardware</li>
   </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
   In the breakout group, time will be provided for researchers to
   demonstrate their achivements and position.  If you have something
   to present, please <a href="contact.xml">let us know</a> and we
   will provide you with presentation time.  You may also publish
   information on this web site in order to let participants get some
   idea of what you are working on in advance.
   <strong>
    The number of workshop participants is limited!  If you want to
    attend, it is mandatory that you first contact <a
    href="mailto:pc@p-cos.net">Pascal Costanza</a>
    before registering through the ECOOP06 web site.
   </strong>
  </p>
  <p>
   We hope that the breakout group will help in advancing dynamic
   hardware and provide for a place for researchers and practitioners
   to work together.
  </p>
 </page>
