<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="website.xsl" ?>
 <page name="secd" title="Reimplementing the SECD microprocessor"
       author="Hans Hübner" email="hans.huebner@gmail.com">
  <p>
   In order to have an achievable goal which will lead in the
   direction of the ultimate dynamic machine, I have been working on a
   reimplementation of the <a
   href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SECD_machine"
   target="_new">SECD</a> microprocessor during the last months.  SECD
   is an abstract machine invented by Peter J. Landin which has been
   used as a basis for various implementations of functional
   programming languages.  It has traditionally been implemented in
   software.
  </p>
  <p>
   The SECD Microprocessor has been developed at the University of
   Calgary in 1980 as part of a microprocessor verification project.
   The results of this projects are available and well documented, so
   it gives a good starting point for working with hardware for
   dynamic programming.
  </p>
  <p>
   When the SECD microprocessor was developed, VLSI design was in it's
   infancy.  Standardized hardware description languages were
   unavailable and it was common practice to write software tools for
   chip design while working at the target implementation - especially
   when it came to research topics like CPUs for functional
   programming.  Still, there have been two physical versions of the
   SECD microprocessor, but it took a year to get the first version of
   the chip actually produced.  When it arrived in the hands of the
   researchers, it contained production faults that totally prevented
   it from working.  The second version of the chip worked (in that it
   was able to execute some programs), but it also had design defects
   that prevented it from being excercised fully.  The high cost and
   long turnaround times for chip production prevented the SECD
   Microprocessor from being fully debugged.
  </p>
  <p>
   Today, VLSI design is a field that is commonplace and well
   understood.  Standardized hardware description languages exist, and
   simulators are available that make it possible to exercise designs
   early in the development cycle - long before they hit the silicon.
   Furthermore, the availability of low-priced, high density field
   programmable gate arrays (FPGAs) radically shorten the
   design-implement-test-cycle for hardware from months and years to
   hours and minutes.
  </p>
  <p>
   The papers about the SECD microprocessor mostly look at it from the
   perspective of proving the correctness of a CPU.  The discussion of
   the processor and its design is not going very deep, as the concern
   of the research group was formally proving the correctness of the
   CPU design, not describing all the implementation details.  Yet,
   the documentation details the register architecture, clocking
   scheme, chip interfacing and microcode.  The full microcode for the
   CPU is available as part of the proof, which could be converted to
   a readable microcode listing.  Working from the microcode listing,
   a synthesizable VHDL model of the SECD microprocessor was created.
  </p>
  <p>
   The SECD reengineering project is thought as a exercise to gain
   working knowledge of current IC design tools in the context of
   dynamic programming languages.  Therefore, it is a goal to preserve
   the original SECD microprocessor design and concentrate on
   converting it to current technology.
  </p>
  <p>
   During the process, it was found that some of the basic design
   decisions where unsuitable to be directly converted to an FPGA
   based design.  In particular, the datapath of the CPU was latch
   based.  Latch-based designs are not well supported by current FPGAs
   because flip flops built into their basic design blocks are D-type
   flip flops which are intended to be driven by a limited number of
   clock signals.  RS-flip flops can only be emulated on a limited
   scale.  Also, the design tool in use could not properly handle the
   large latch-based data path.  Thus, the architecture needed some
   tactical changes in order to be implemented on the FPGA technology
   available.
  </p>
  <p>
   Converting the design from latches to clocked flip flops also
   required changing the microcode.  In the original design, the
   garbage collector uses generic ALU operations to iterate over the
   address space and manipulate the garbage collection bits of the
   data words.  This usage of the ALU is non-orthogonal to the rest of
   the ALU usage, making it harder to implement a clocking scheme in
   the datapath.  Therefore, the garbage collection arithmetic was
   seperated from the user arithmetic.
  </p>
  <p>
   The current version of the VHDL model of the SECD CPU synthesizes
   to about 90.000 gate equivalent using Xilinx WebPack ISE 8.1
   targeted at a Spartan-3 FPGA.  Thus, it does fit well into one of
   the current low-cost FPGA development boards.  In fact, even the
   lower-density chips provide 200.000 gate equivalents, so there is
   enough room for application specific logic to be added to the
   model.  The free version of the ISE synthesis tools support
   Spartan-3 FPGAs up to 1 Million gate equivalents, so even versions
   of the CPU which have multiple evaluators will fit into the
   low-cost devices available.
  </p>
  <p>
   Performance was a non-goal for the design of the SECD
   microprocessor, and as such it is expected that the FPGA based SECD
   will not be very fast.  Two major limiting factors for the
   limited performance of the CPU are believed to be:
   <ul>
    <li>
     <strong>
      List-based storage with inefficient traversal of the list
      structures.
     </strong>
     All memory is organized as lists, which makes all memory
     operations expensive.
    </li>
    <li>
     <strong>
      Variable-lookup in the environment through numeric indices.
     </strong>
     In order to lookup a variable in a given environment, a numeric
     index is used.  The CPU traverses the memory lists until the
     numbered data item is found.
    </li>
   </ul>
   It is clear that these two design decisions have severe influences
   on the overall performance of the processor.  Yet, the high clock
   rates that can be achieved with current silicon may be able to
   compensate at least for some of the low performance of the design.
   Final performance analysis will need to be done at a later stage,
   and there are several optimization strategies available for SECD
   based systems that can be implemented in order to enhance the
   performance of the processor.
  </p>
  <p>
   The usefulness of the original SECD microprocessor is limited by
   the fact that it solely supports a recursive functional execution
   model.  There are no destructive operations, and the processor is
   designed as a coprocessor to a conventional CPU.  The host CPU sets
   up the memory image for the SECD CPU.  The SECD CPU evaluates the
   top-level expression and halts once the evaluation is complete.
   The host CPU then reads the resulting memory image which is the
   result of the evaluation.  In order to make the SECD CPU useful for
   stand-alone applications, some form of non-recursive looping is
   needed.  The LispMe Scheme system can be used as a model for
   extending the SECD ISA to support the features needed for running
   Scheme.
  </p>
  <p>
   The reimplementation of SECD is written in VHDL and targeted to
   Xilinx Spartan-3 FPGA.  A <a
   href="http://trenz-electronic.de/prod/prodde21.htm">Retrocomputing
   Base Board</a> by <a href="http://trenz-electronic/">trenz
   electronic</a> is used for peripherals.  As of now, only the SRAM
   of the base board is used.  The host CPU, which downloads the
   program to the SECD CPU's RAM and displays back the result, is also
   implemented within the FPGA and based on the <a
   href="http://members.optushome.com.au/jekent/system09/index.html">System09</a>
   SoC.
  </p>
  <p>
   The current version of the VHDL implementation can be checked out
   of the Subversion repository at svn://1blu.huebner.org/trunk/secd
   for reference.  There will be a formal release once the hardware
   synthesis has been completed and tested.  For the time being,
   the Subversion repository is a work in progress and may or may
   not work at any point in time.
  </p>
  <p>
   I have to thank <a href="http://www.evision-systems.de/">eVision
   Systems GmbH</a> and <a href="http://aldec.com/">Aldec</a> for
   letting me use their excellent <a
   href="http://aldec.com/products/active%2Dhdl/">Active-HDL</a> VHDL
   design tool for free.  Without Active-HDL, I would have been stuck
   early in the process.  Using the Perl API of Active-HDL, I was able
   to programmatically examine the simulated SECD's memory and
   compare the memory state to that produced by a software SECD.
   This was an unvaluable tool to find several bugs.
  </p>
  <links>
   <group name="SECD">
    <link title="SECD Mania" href="http://skelet.ludost.net/sec/">
     is a page dedicated to the SECD virtual machine.  It
     points to various implementations of the SECD VM as well as other
     useful information.
    </link>
    <link title="LispMe SECD based Scheme Interpreter" href="http://lispme.de/lispme/">
     The LispMe Scheme system is a SECD based Scheme system for PalmOS.
    </link>
    <link title="HOL proof for the SECD microprocessor" href="http://www.ftp.cl.cam.ac.uk/ftp/hvg/hol88/contrib/SECD/">
     Formal verification of the correctness of the
     SECD microprocessor.  It contains, in theorem form, the microcode
     of the CPU as well as other useful information for recreating the
     CPU.
    </link>
    <link title="The SECD Microprocessor papers at University of Calgary" href="http://pharos.cpsc.ucalgary.ca/Dienst/UI/2.0/Query/?title=secd&amp;authority=ncstrl.ucalgary_cs">
     describe various aspects of the SECD microprocessor,
     focusing on the formal correctness proof.  They are the primary
     source for the reimplementation of the CPU.
    </link>
    <link title="LispKit Port to GNU Pascal" href="http://lispkit.members.beeb.net/">
     is a port of the original LispKit source, which is a software
     implementation of SECD with a LispKit compiler written in
     LispKit.  The distributions contains the virtual machine
     implementation as well as several LispKit programs, both
     in compiled and (scrambled) source form.
    </link>
   </group>
   <group name="FPGA based CPUs">
    <link title="R16: a New Transputer for FPGAs" href="http://wotug.org/paperdb/send_file.php?num=151">
     details the architecture of the FPGA based R16 transputer system.
     It adresses many issues that are relevant to the design of a LISP
     system, in particular with respect to the design of the memory
     system.
    </link>
    <link title="Design of a Transputer Core and its Implementation in an FPGA" href="http://www.wotug.org/paperdb/send_file.php?num=125">
     describes the implementation of a Inmos Transputer work-alike on
     an FPGA.
    </link>
    <link title="OpenCores" href="http://opencores.org/">
     is a website that focuses on promoting the use of free IP cores.
     A number of CPU IP cores is available from here, as well as
     numerous other peripheral IP cores.
    </link>
   </group>
   <group name="Classic Designs">
    <link title="The SCHEME-79 Chip" href="http://www.bitsavers.org/pdf/mit/ai/aim/AIM-559.pdf">
     is a chip designed to execute scheme.  The paper
     describes the general design of the chip and contains a microcode
     listing.
    </link>
    <link title="Konzeption, Entwurf und Realisierung eines Prozessors für die funktionale Programmiersprache Scheme als VLSI-Chip in Standard- und Makrozellentechnik"
          href="http://tams-www.informatik.uni-hamburg.de/paper/1990/lohse-diss/dissertation_lohse.ps.Z">
     is the doctoral thesis of Jörg Lohse in which he describes the
     SCHEME-1 CPU that he designed and implemented.  The CPU worked as
     a coprocessor to an Atari ST and used some 70.000 transistors
     (german).
    </link>
    <link title="The Scheme Machine" href="http://www.cs.indiana.edu/pub/techreports/TR413.pdf">
     Is another design for a machine executing compiled Scheme.
    </link>
    <link title="Jaap Weel's LISP Machine Page" href="http://www.ugcs.caltech.edu/~weel/lispm.html">
     contains a comprehensive collection of links to
     LISP machine related information.
    </link>
    <link title="The Mushroom Project" href="http://www.wolczko.com/mushroom/index.html">
     aimed at creating a machine to execute
     Smalltalk.  It's architecture shared several of the features LISP
     machines provide.
    </link>
    <link title="The LMI K-Machine" href="http://home.comcast.net/~prunesquallor/kmachine.htm">
     was the last machine developed by Lisp Machines Incorporated.
    </link>
   </group>
   <group name="Hardware">
    <link title="Plastic Cell Architecture (PCA)" href="http://www.cis.nagasaki-u.ac.jp/labs/oguri/">
     is a
     Sea-of-Gates-Style reconfigurable hardware architecture with a 
     regular layout and fine-grained reconfigurability.
    </link>
    <link title="Xilinx XC6200" href="http://www.dcs.gla.ac.uk/~nicholas/ca4/dsheet.pdf">
     FPGA architecture supporting fast incremental reconfiguration
     by a host computer through a parallel interface.  No longer in
     production.
    </link>
    <link title="Spartan-3E Starter Kit" href="http://www.xilinx.com/s3estarter/">
     - a low-cost (~$150) development for
     Xilinx Spartan-3E FPGAs.  The kit contains a 500K gate FPGA as well
     as a large number of peripherals that make it useful for SoC
     designs.  It comes bundled with development software media and
     Xilinx provides several real-world example designs.
    </link>
    <link title="Trenz Electronic Spartan-3 Micromodule" href="http://www.trenz-electronic.de/prod/proden18.htm">
      + Retrocomputing base board
     make an inexpensive development solution providing for a high
     density FPGA (1 Mio gates) and a number of useful peripherals.
    </link>
   </group>
   <group name="Books">
    <book title="The Architecture of Symbolic Computers"
          author="Peter M. Kogge"
          isbn="0070355967"
          year="1990">
     This book describes a number of symbolic computer architectures
     targeted at functional and logic programming.  It details the
     underlying mathematical principles as well as implementations in
     real hardware.
    </book>
    <book title="The SECD Microprocessor - A Verification Case Study"
          author="Brian T. Graham"
          isbn="0792392450"
          year="1992">
     This book describes the hardware verification project in which
     the correctness of the SECD microprocessor was partially
     verified.
    </book>
   </group>
  </links>
 </page>
